# Johannes Nicolaus Wibisana

#### PHD STUDENT

Onna-son, Okinawa, Japan

【 (+81) 50-3707-5757 | 🗷 johannes.nicolaus@oist.jp | 🛠 www.jnicolaus.com | 🖸 johannesnicolaus | 🛅 johannes-nicolaus | 🛣 JN Wibisana

# Summary.

I am a 2nd year PhD student at the Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology at the Genomics and Regulatory Systems Unit. I am currently working to investigate the epigenetic basis of transcriptional regulation in the pelagic tunicate *Oikopleura dioica*. Previously, I have used single-cell omics and fluorescence imaging analysis to investigate NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell. I am familiar with R, ImageJ macro and bash programming languages for image processing and analysis of multi-omics data. I also have experience with basic molecular biology experiments such as mammalian and avian cell culture, RNA-FISH, molecular cloning, genome editing and qPCR. Being highly adaptable and proactive, I am keen and can quickly grasp new concepts that can be applied to my current and future research.

# **Education**

## **Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology**

Okinawa, Japan

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY Apr. 2022 - Present

- Epigenetic landscape in the cryptic species of Oikopleura dioica. Genomics and Regulatory Systems Unit (Pl: Nicholas Luscombe)
- Rotation projects:

  Investigation of dontal relationships

Investigation of dental microwear analysis in fish-tetrapod transition. Macroevolution Unit (PI: Lauren Sallan)
Investigation of metabolic-related gene duplication in pomacentridae. Marine Eco-Evo-Devo Unit (PI: Vincent Laudet)

#### **Osaka University (Graduate School of Science)**

Osaka, Japan

M.S.C IN BIOLOGICAL SCIENCES Apr. 2020 - Mar. 2022

- Thesis research: NF-kB transcriptional regulation in B-cell, Laboratory for Cell Systems (PI: Mariko Okada)
- Awardee of the Honjo International Scholarship Foundation scholarship
- Others: In charge of laboratory website and bioinformatics training of visiting researchers

#### Osaka University (Graduate School of Science)

Osaka, Japan

Oct 2016 - Mar 2020

- Thesis research: NF-kB transcriptional regulation in B-cell, Laboratory for Cell Systems (PI: Mariko Okada)
- Awardee of the MEXT scholarship
- Selected for the AEARU 2018 Summer Camp in Hefei China
- Qualified for early graduation

## **Publications**

B.Sc in Biological Sciences

# RESEARCH ARTICLES

Type 2 helper T cells convert into Interleukin-13-expressing follicular helper T cells after antigen repriming

Translational and Regulatory

Sciences

Y Harada, T Sasaki, **JN Wibisana**, M Okada, C Liu, H Ueno, PD Burrows, M Kubo

2022

JN WIBISANA, T INABA, H SHINOHARA, N YUMOTO, T HAYASHI, M UMEDA, M EBISAWA, I NIKAIDO, Y SAKO, M OKADA

PLoS Genetics

ASURAT: functional annotation-driven unsupervised clustering of single-cell

Enhanced transcriptional heterogeneity mediated by NF-кВ super-enhancers

Bioinformatics

K IIDA, J KONDO, **JN WIBISANA**, M INOUE, M OKADA

2022

#### **REVIEW ARTICLES**

JN WIBISANA, M OKADA

Encoding and decoding NF-кВ nuclear dynamics

Current Opinion in Cell Biology

2022

Prediction of transcriptional regulation in immune cells through single-cell analysis

Journal of Clinical and Experimental Medicine (Igaku no Ayumi)

JN Wibisana, K Iida, M Okada

2021

### **BOOK CHAPTER**

Quantitative imaging analysis of NF-kB for mathematical modelling applications

Methods in Molecular Biology

JN WIBISANA, T INABA, Y SAKO, M OKADA

2023

# **Presentations**

#### INTERNATIONAL

## Imaging and single-cell sequencing analysis of super-enhancer activation mediated by NF-kB in B cells

Online

CELL SYMPOSIA: BIOLOGICAL ASSEMBLIES - PHASE TRANSITIONS AND MORE (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Nov 2021

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

Online May 2021

COLD SPRING HARBOR LABORATORY BIOLOGY OF GENOMES 2021 (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Seoul, South Korea

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

Japan-Korea Bilateral Symposium between IPR and SNU on Advanced Analysis of Protein Function and

Jan. 2020

STRUCTURE (ORAL PRESENTATION)

Okinawa, Japan

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE OF SYSTEMS BIOLOGY (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Nov. 2019

#### DOMESTIC

#### Enhancer-mediated transcriptional regulation in Oikopleura dioica

Chiba, Japan

THE 45TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE MOLECULAR BIOLOGY SOCIETY OF JAPAN (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Nov. 2022

Imaging and single-cell sequencing analysis of super-enhancer activation mediated by NF-kB in B cells

Online

19TH IPR RETREAT (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Nov. 2021

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

Online

THE 58TH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE BIOPHYSICAL SOCIETY OF JAPAN (POSTER PRESENTATION)

Sep. 2020 Osaka, Japan

NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell

Nov. 2019

18TH IPR RETREAT (ORAL PRESENTATION)

# Research Experience

# Genomics and Regulatory Systems Unit (PI: Nicholas Luscombe), Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology

Okinawa, Japan Mar. 2022 - Present

• Project: Epigenetic landscape in the cryptic species O. dioica

Analysis of RNA-seq, ATAC-seq, CAGE, and other epigenetic sequencing data

• Improved genome annotation of O. dioica

# Macroevolution Unit (PI: Lauren Sallan), Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology

Okinawa, Japan

PhD Rotation student

PhD STUDENT

2023

- Project: Investigation of dental microwear analysis in fish-tetrapod transition
- Established fish facility for Polypterus
- Performed dental molding of fossils and subsequent scanning using confocal microscope

# Marine Eco-Evo-Devo Unit (PI: Vincent Laudet), Okinawa Institute of Science and **Technology**

Okinawa, Japan

PHD ROTATION STUDENT 2022

- Project: Investigation of metabolic gene duplication in clownfish
- · Performed gene duplication analysis using computational phylogenetic analysis
- Performed fish dissection for RNA extraction and subsequent qPCR analysis

#### Laboratory for Cell Systems (PI: Mariko Okada), Osaka University

Osaka, Japan

Undergraduate - Master's student

Feb. 2019 - Mar. 2022

- Project: NF-κB mediated transcriptional regulation in B cell
- Performed quantitative imaging analysis of NF-κB nuclear translocation using confocal microscope and ImageJ
- Performed single-cell RNA-seq and single-cell ATAC-seq analysis to find the relationship between cis-regulatory elements and gene expression
- Performed single-molecule RNA-FISH and qPCR for the confirmation of RNA-seq results
- · Performed cloning for both transient and permanent expression of fluorescent-tagged protein of interest
- In charge of side projects concerning RNA-seq analysis and training of visiting researchers on RNA-seq analysis

#### Laboratory of Science and Innovation for Pain, Osaka University

Osaka, Japan

RESEARCH ASSISTANT Apr. 2018 - Feb. 2019

- · Performed mouse genotyping, RNA extraction and ELISA
- Performed image analysis of mouse MRI images
- In charge of laboratory cleanliness

#### Bio Medical Wet Robotics Laboratory (PI: Morishima Keisuke), Osaka University

Osaka, Japan

ASSOCIATE PROJECT LEADER FOR OSAKA UNIVERSITY BIOMOD 2017-2018

2017-2018

- · Performed basic DNA origami experiments
- Performed 3D modeling and computer simulated DNA origami design

#### Laboratory of Cellular Life Science (PI: Naotada Ishihara), Osaka University

Osaka, Japan

Sep. 2018 - Feb. 2019

- Project: Quantification of Mitochondrial Morphology
- Performed quantitative analysis of mitochondrial morphology using ImageJ
- · Performed basic experiments such as mammalian cell culture and confocal imaging

# **Honors & Awards**

Apr. 2020 - Honjo International Scholarship Foundation Scholarship

Mar. 2022

Sep. 2020 Poster presentation award, The 58th Annual meeting of the Biophysical Society of Japan

2018 Bronze award, BIOMOD 2018 Molecular Design Competition

2017 Bronze award, BIOMOD 2017 Molecular Design Competition

U.S.A.

Sep. 2016 - MEXT scholarship

Mar. 2020

RESEARCH INTERN

# Workshops \_\_\_\_\_

Dec. 2022 EMBO Practical Course: Single-cell omics: deeper to genomics

Heidelberg,

Germany

Jul. 2020 第 30 回細胞生物学ワークショップ

Hyogo, Japan

# **Qualifications**

2019 **N1**, Japanese Language Proficiency Test

# **Organizations**

2019-2021 **Secretary General**, Indonesian Student Association in Japan

2018-2019 **President**, Indonesian Student Association in Japan (Osaka-Nara)

# Other skills

Website development HTML, CSS (Bootstrap), Jekyll.

**3D printing and modeling** Basic 3D modeling using Fusion360 and Maya. Familiar with basic 3D printing techniques.